<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<exercises>
<instruction> Answer the questions based on the conversation.  A refers to the first speaker, B the second.  Click "Show" for the scripts and the answers. </instruction>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/218419169382.mp3" >a) Based on the speech style, describe the
relationship between A and B.    
b) What does A want to know? 
c) Does B know?
</question>
<answer >A: あの人、だれ？
B: どの人？
A: あそこでタバコを吸（す）っている人。
B: さあ、知（し）らないけど、、。
 
a) Based on the speech style, describe the
relationship between A and B.      (Friends)
b) What does A want to know? (Identity of a person smoking over there.)
c) Does B know?   (She
doesn’t know.)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/234182413275.mp3" >a) What does A ask? 
b) What is B’s response? 
</question>
<answer >A: この傘（かさ）がいる人、いますか。
B: みんな、持（も）っているから、だれもいらないと思いますよ。
 
a) What does A ask? (‘Are there anyone who needs this umbrella?’)
b) What is B’s response? (B
doesn’t think anyone needs it. Everyone has one)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/569055372224.mp3" >a) What is being discussed? 
b) Why does B think it is popular?  
c) In what context, is Friday mentioned.   
</question>
<answer >A: あの映画（えいが）、人気（にんき）がありますねえ。
B: そうですね、トム・クルーズが出ているからじゃないですか。
A: もう見ましたか。
B: いいえ、あの映画（えいが）は金曜日に始（はじ）まると思いますよ。
 
a) What is being discussed?  (A
movie.)
b) Why does B think it is popular?  (Because Tom Cruise is in it.)
c) In what context, is Friday mentioned.     (The movie
starts on Friday.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/971769339013.mp3" >a) What
does A ask Kimura to do?  
b) Why
does B (Kimura) apologize?  
</question>
<answer >A: 木村（きむら）さん、すみませんけど、これを教（おし）えてください。
B: 私は分かりませんから、コンピュータをよく知（し）っている人に聞（き）いてください。すみません。
 
a) What
does A ask Kimura to do?  (Teach
her something)
b) Why
does B (Kimura) apologize?   (She doesn’t know it, so she
apologized.  She
told A to ask someone who knows computers.)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/909121799822.mp3" >a) Who is A looking for? 
b) Describe the person in question. 
</question>
<answer >A: ちょっとすみません。
B: はい。
A: あのう、林（はやし）さんはどの人ですか。
B: 林（はやし）さんですか。青（あお）いジャケットを着（き）ている人です。
A: どうも。 
 a) Who is A looking for?   (Hayashi)
b) Describe the person in question.   (He is wearing a blue
shirt.) 
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >a) What does A ask B? 
b) What is B going to do now? 
</question>
<answer >A: お風呂（ふろ）に入（はい）った？
B: まだ入（はい）っていないよ。
A: 今から入（はい）る？
B: ううん、お寺（てら）までちょっと散歩（さんぽ）してくる。
 
a) What does A ask B?  (If B has
taken a bath?)
b) What is B going to do now? (Taking a little walk to a temple.)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/354966623083.mp3" >a) What event is discussed?
b) Did B go? 
c) How about A? 
d) What is A concerned? 
e) How does B respond? 
</question>
<answer >A: おとといのアカペラのコンサート、聴（き）きに行った？
B: ううん、病気（びょうき）だったから、行かなかった。
A: それは残念（ざんねん）だったねえ。 
B: 行った？
A: うん、切符（きっぷ）を二枚（まい）もらったから、友だちと一緒に行って来た。ところで、もう大丈夫（だいじょうぶ）？薬（くすり）は飲んだ？
B: うん、もう大丈夫（だいじょうぶ）だよ。ありがとう。
  
 a) What event is discussed? (A cappella concert two days ago)
b) Did B go?   (No,
because she was sick.)
c) How about A?   (A went
with her friend because she got two tickets from someone.)
d) What is A concerned?  (If B is all right.  She asked if B took medicine.)
e) How does B respond?  (‘I am already fine. Thanks.’)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >a) Who
is B?
b) What
does A want to know? 
c) What surprises B? 
</question>
<answer >A: 鈴木（すずき）さん、鈴木（すずき）さんはタバコを吸（す）う女の人をどう思いますか。
B: え？僕（ぼく）？うん、そうだねえ、、、。時々かっこいいと思うけど、、、。
A: 本当（ほんとう）ですか？
 
a) Who
is B?   (Suzuki)
b) What
does A want to know? (A wants to know what
B thinks about women who smoke.) 
c) What surprises B?  (A is
surprised because B sometimes thinks they are cool.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/554710187091.mp3" >a) What does B say about her older
brother?
b) What does B say about herself? 
</question>
<answer >A: 山田さんのお兄（にい）さんは子どもの時（とき）はどんな子だった？
B: 兄（あに）は頭（あたま）がよくて、いい子だったよ。
A: 山田さんは？
B: 私は静（しず）かな子だったと思う。小さいときはたいてい一人で遊（あそ）んでいた。
 
a) What does B say about her older
brother?   (He
was smart and good when he was a child.)
b) What does B say about herself?   (She was a quiet child. She used to play alone
when she was small.)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/520353218148.mp3" >a) Based on their speech style, describe the
relationship between A and B? 
b) What does A invite B to do?
c) Does B accept? 
</question>
<answer >A: 水野（みずの）さん、金曜日の晩（ばん）、何かする？　　　
B: 別（べつ）に何もしないと思いますけど、、。
A: じゃあ、 踊（おど）りに行かない？
B: ええ。ぜひ！
 
a) Based on their speech style, describe the
relationship between A and B? (A = superior, B = subordinate)
b) What does A invite B to do? 
(To go dancing.)c) Does B accept? (Yes. B said 'By all means!')
 </answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/288129528825.mp3" >a) Where does this conversation take place?  
b) What does buy? 
</question>
<answer >A: いらっしゃいませ。
B: チーズバーガーを三つとダブルバーガーを一つ下さい。
A: はい、お飲物（のみもの）は？
B: アイスコーヒーとシェイクを二つお願（ねが）いします。
A: はい、アイスコーヒーはお一つですね。ありがとうございます。
 
a) Where does this conversation take place?  (Hamburger
shop.)
b) What does buy?  (Two
cheeseburgers, One double burger, One ice coffee, two shakes.) 
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/722980746141.mp3" >a) What
permission does A request?
b) What is
B’s initial reaction? 
c) What is A’s response? 
</question>
<answer >A: すみません。今日はもう帰ってもいいですか。
B: え？どうして？
A: 今子どもから電話（でんわ）があって、病気（びょうき）だと言っていますから、医者（いしゃ）のところに連（つ）れて行きます。すみません。
 
a) What
permission does A request?  (A wants to go home now.)
b) What is
B’s initial reaction? (B asked the reason.)
c) What is A’s response?  (A’s
child just called her and said he is sick.  So, A is going to take him to a doctor.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/399601355734.mp3" >a) Describe the relationship between A and
B.     
b) What does B do tonight? 
c) What will Mika going to do now? 
d) What is A concerned?  
e) What is Mika’s response?
</question>
<answer >A: 宿題（しゅくだい）、やった？
B:まだ、全然（ぜんぜん）始（はじ）めていないよ。今からやる。みかさんは？A: 私はもう終（おわ）ったから、寝（ね）るわ。
B: 明日（あした）、英語の試験（しけん）があるけど、単語（たんご）はもう覚（おぼ）えた？ 
A: 単語（たんご）は明日（あした）の朝（あさ）、勉強（べんきょう）する。おやすみなさい。
B: 本当（ほんとう）に大丈夫（だいじょうぶ）？ 
A: 大丈夫、大丈夫。
 
a) Describe the relationship between A and
B.     
(Friends)
b) What does B do tonight? (B
will probably do homework)
c) What will Mika going to do now? (She
will go to bed because she has finished her homework.)
d) What is A concerned?  (There’s an English exam tomorrow and if Mika
has memorized vocabulary)
e) What is Mika’s response? (She
will study vocabulary tomorrow morning.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/939465819466.mp3" >a) What is Takahashi going to
travel?  Give details. 
b) Why is A going there? 
c) According to Takahashi, what is the place like? 
d) What comment does B make regarding the place.
</question>
<answer >A: 私、水曜日から旅行（りょこう）に行ってきます。
B: 高橋（たかはし）さんは旅行（りょこう）するのが好（す）きですねえ。今度（こんど）はどこですか。
A: 長野（ながの）の温泉（おんせん）です。先月も行きましたけど、私、あそこは大好（だいす）きだから。
B: どんなところですか。
A: ちょっと寂（さび）しいところですけど、雑誌（ざっし）に出たから、今は人気（にんき）がありますよ。若（わか）い人もたくさん来（く）ると思います。
B: 長野（ながの）は東京から新幹線（しんかんせん）があるから、便利（べんり）ですね。
 
a) What is Takahashi going to
travel?  Give details.  (She will go to Onsen in Nagano.)
b) Why is A going there?  (She likes it.)
c) According to Takahashi, what is the place like? (A bit lonely place. But it is popular now
because it was introduced in a magazine. 
She thinks a lot of young people come there.)
d) What comment does B make regarding the place.  (It is convenient to go because there’s
Shinkansen from Tokyo”
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/883713858508.mp3" >a) Where
is A going? Why?
b) What does A ask B? 
c) What is B’s initial
response? 
d) Why does B eventually ask A
to do? 
</question>
<answer >A: コンビニにお弁当（べんとう）を買（か）いに行きますけど、何かいりますか。
B: いや、別（べつ）に。私はもうお昼（ひる）ご飯（はん）を食べましたから。
A: そうですか。
B: あ、すみません、ちょっと待（ま）ってください。すみませんけど、ペンがないから、買って来てください。　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　
A: 分かりました。色（いろ）は？
B: 赤（あか）いペンをお願（ねが）いします。
A: はい。じゃあ、行ってきます。
 
a) Where
is A going? Why?  (A is going to a convenience store to buy boxed lunch.)
b) What does A ask B? (If she needs anything.)
c) What is B’s initial
response?  (She
doesn’t need anything because she has already eaten lunch.) 
d) Why does B eventually ask A
to do? (To buy a red pen.) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/564134861416.mp3" >a)
Where are clips? 
b) How
many? 
c) What does B offer to do?
Why?
d) What is A’s response to the
offer?   
</question>
<answer >A: その机（つくえ）の上にクリップがありませんか。　
B: ええ。 A: いくつありますか。
B: ええと、白（しろ）いクリップが八つと青（あお）いクリップが十あります。
A: 緑（みどり）のクリップは？
B: ぜんぜんありませんから、買（か）って来（き）ましょうか。
A: いや、今日は店がお休（やす）みだから、明日（あした）買って来てください。お願（ねが）いします。
 
a)
Where are clips?  (On the desk near B)
b) How
many?   (Eight white ones and ten blue ones)
c) What does B offer to do?
Why?  (Go buy green clips because there
aren’t any.)
d) What is A’s response to the
offer?    (The store is closed today, so please go tomorrow.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/409687534746.mp3" >a) What
item is being discussed? 
b) Describe the item.  
c) How does B acquire them? 
</question>
<answer >A: その靴（くつ）、かわいいね。
B: そう？ありがとう。
A: 色（いろ）がとてもきれい。新（あたら）しい靴（くつ）？
B: うん、山本君（くん）に誕生日（たんじょうび）にもらった。
A: ええっ、、、山本君はガールフレンドがいると思っていたけど、、、。
B: いや、あのう、、、。
 
a) What
item is being discussed? (B’s shoes.)
b) Describe the item.  (Cute and
nice. Color is beautiful. New.)
c) How does B acquire them? (B got them from Yamamoto.)
d) Why is A surprised?  (Because
A thought Yamamoto has a girlfriend.)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/191852126809.mp3" >a) What do A and B have in common?
b) What does B (Yasuda) sometimes do? 
 c) What does A (Takahashi) do on her day-off? 
</question>
<answer >A: 安田（やすだ）さんはどんな運動（うんどう）をしていますか。
B: 僕（ぼく）は運動（うんどう）するのが嫌（きら）いですから、あまりしていませんねえ。まあ、時々（ときどき）家内（かない）と散歩（さんぽ）しますけど、、、。木村（きむら）さんは？　
A: 私もあまり好（す）きじゃないです。
B: 休みは何をしていますか。
A: たいてい遅（おそ）く起（お）きて、それから、ピアノを弾（ひ）いていますよ。
B: へえ、そうですか。
 
a) What do A and B have in common?  (Neither
of them likes exercising.)
b) What does B (Yasuda) sometimes do? (Take
a walk with his wife.)
c) What does A (Takahashi) do on her day-off?  (She gets up late and plays
piano.) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/510134766883.mp3" >a) Why does A apologize?   
b) What does B tell A about the meeting?  
c) What does B urge A to do?  (To hurry.)
d) Who does B ask A about? 
Why?
e) What is B’s response?
</question>
<answer >A: 遅（おそ）くなってすみません。竹田（たけだ）先生は？
B: あ、京子さん。ミーティングはさっき始（はじ）まりましたよ。隣（となり）の部屋（へや）です。急（いそ）いでください。
あ、京子さん、ちょっと待（ま）ってください。
A: はい。
B: 北島（きたじま）さんがまだ来（き）ていませんけど、何か聞（き）いていますか。
A: いえ、私は何も、、、。
B: そうですか。
 
 
a) Why does A apologize?   (A was late for a meeting.)
b) What does B tell A about the meeting?  (It has begun a while ago in the next room.)
c) What does B urge A to do?  (To hurry.)
d) Who does B ask A about? 
Why?  (About Kitajima.  He has
not come yet.  B wondered if A has
heard anything.)
e) What is B’s response?   (She has
not heard anything.)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >a) Describe the relationship between A and B.
b) What is B going to do tonight? Why?
c) What is A going to do now?
d) What is B's concern?
e) What is A's response?
</question>
<answer >A: 英語のクラスの作文さくぶんは終おわった？B: まだ全然ぜんぜん始はじめていない。A: 私はもう全部ぜんぶやったから、寝ねるよ。B: 明日あしたは中国語の試験しけんもあるけど、だいじょうぶ？単語たんごはもう覚おぼえた？A: まだ。でも、朝あさ早はやく起おきて勉強べんきょうする。B: そう。おやすみ。A: おやすみ。a) Describe the relationship between A and B.Friends.
b) What is B going to do tonight? Why?B is going to write essay for her English class. She hasn't started yet.
c) What is A going to do now?She will go to bed.  She has already finished her English essay.
d) What is B's concern?There is an exam in Chinese class tomorrow but A has not memorized vocabulary.
e) What is A's response?She has not.  She will get up early tomorrow morning and study.</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >a)What event does A invite B to?
b) Who will appear at the event? Give details.
c) Does B accept the invitation?
</question>
<answer >A: 友だちにもらったコンサートの切符きっぷが二枚まいありますけど、よかったら行きませんか。B: だれのコンサートですか。A: ピンクです。私はよく知らないけど、友だちが有名ゆうめいな人だと言っていました。B: じゃあ、ぜひ。a)What event does A invite B to?Concert.  A got two tickets from her friend.
b) Who will appear at the event? Give details."Pink" will appear. "Pink" is a famous female singer.
c) Does B accept the invitation?Yes. </answer>
</exercise>
</exercises>
