<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<exercises>
<instruction> Answer the questions based on the conversation.  A refers to the first speaker, B the second.  Click "Show" for the scripts and the answers. </instruction>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/368045106138.mp3" >a) What does A suggest?
b) What does B ask?
c) What is A’ response? 
</question>
<answer >A: 来週(らいしゅう）、みんなでミーティングをしましょう。
B: わかりました。火曜と木曜と金曜の中でいつが一番（いちばん）いいですか。
A:  木曜日が一番いいですけど、いいですか。
B: 結構（けっこう）です。
 
a) What does A suggest?  (To have a meeting all
together.)
b) What does B ask?   (Which day is best, Tue, Thur.
or Fri.?)
c) What is A’ response?  (Thursday is.) 
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/968995699034.mp3" >a) What is the topic of this conversation? 
b) What does A want to know?
c) What is B’s response?  
d) What does A ask B to do? 
</question>
<answer >A: この野菜(やさい）の料理（りょうり）、冷（つめ）たくておいしいですねえ。どうやって作（つく）りましたか。
B: 簡単（かんたん）ですよ。母にレシピをもらいました。
A: ぜひ、私にも下さい。
 
a) What is the topic of this conversation? (Cold vegetable dishes B made.)
b) What does A want to know? (How B made it.)
c) What is B’s response?  
  (B
said it was easy. She got the recipe from her mother.)d) What does A ask B to do?  (‘Please
give the recipe to me, too’.) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/665412365765.mp3" >a) Which places are discussed? 
b) How long was B there?   
c) Which place does B like better?  Why?
d) Who else’s view is mentioned?
</question>
<answer >A: 田中さんは東京にも京都（きょうど）にも住（す）んでいましたね。
B: ええ、東京には五ヵ月で、京都には一年いました。
A:  どちらの方（ほう）が好（す）きですか。
B: 東京の方が好きです。にぎやかで楽（たの）しかったですから。でも、主人（しゅじん）は京都の静（しず）かな生活（せいかつ）の方が好きだって言いますけど。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/574246302786.mp3" >a) What will B go tomorrow?
b) What misunderstanding did they
have?
</question>
<answer >A: 明日(あした）、何をするつもり？
B: 明日は美容院（びよういん）の予約（よやく）がある。
A:  病院（びょういん）？
B: ううん、美容院（びよういん）。
 
a) What will B go tomorrow?  (Go to a
beauty parlor.)
b) What misunderstanding did they
have? (A thought B had said ‘byoin’,
hospital.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/201057893763.mp3" >a) What is B trying to decide? 
b) What suggestion does A make? 
</question>
<answer >A: その手袋（てぶくろ）、買（か）う？
B: うん、グレーのと青（あお）いのとどっちがいいと思（おも）う？
A:  青い方（ほう）がかわいくて安（やす）いよ。　
B: じゃあ、この青いのを買うわ。
 
a) What is B trying to decide?   (Which
globes she should buy-gray one or blue.)
b) What suggestion does A make?   (Blue ones are cuter and cheaper.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/775289298574.mp3" >a) What does A notice?   
b) What problem does B have? 
c) What explanation does B provide relating to
her problem? 
d) What comment does A make? 
</question>
<answer >A: 目(め）が赤（あか）くなっているけど、大丈夫（だいじょうぶ）？
B: ちょっと眠（ねむ）いから。
A:  昨日（きのう）は何時間ぐらい寝（ね）た？
B: 五時間ぐらいだった。このごろ仕事が忙（いそが）しくなって、うちに遅（おそ）く帰るから。
A:  大変（たいへん）ね。
 
a) What does A notice?   (B’s eyes are red.)
b) What problem does B have?   (She is a
bit sleepy.)
c) What explanation does B provide relating to
her problem? (She has gotten busy with
work and goes home late these days.)
d) What comment does A make?  (That’s
tough.)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/331238521336.mp3" >a) Who are A and B?
b) What comparison does A make?
c) What is B’s response?  
d)
Describe the rest of the circumstance.
</question>
<answer >A: お母さん、この赤(あか）いノートと白（しろ）いのと、どっちの方（ほう）がきれい？
B: 今日は何も買（か）ってはいけません。
A:  え、でも、ノートがいる。
B: 今日はお金、持（も）っていないから。
A:  お願（ねが）い！
B: 買いません！帰りましょう。
 
a) Who are A and B?   (A= child, B=mother,)
b) What comparison does A make? (‘Which is prettier, red notebook or white one?’)
c) What is B’s response?  (‘You may
not buy anything today.’)
d)
Describe the rest of the circumstance. (B
begged A to buy her a notebook claiming that she needs one, but mother did not
yield.) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/844723611445.mp3" >a) What does A suggest to do?
b) What comparison is being made? 
c) What choice is made? Why? 
</question>
<answer >A: 明日(あした）、一緒（いっしょ）に英語の練習（れんしゅう）をしない？
B: いいよ。図書館（としょかん）と学生センターとどっちがいい？
A: 図書館のほうがいい。あそこ、便利（べんり）になったよ。
B: わかった。じゃあ、二時に図書館で。A: オッケー。
 
a) What does A suggest to do?  (They
practice English together.)
b) What comparison is being made?  (Between the library and student center, which
is better?)
c) What choice is made? Why?  (A
prefers the library because it has become convenient.)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/762887513105.mp3" >a) What does A notice?   
b) What information does B provide? 
</question>
<answer >  A: あ、たけしさんの隣(となり）にだれか座（すわ）っていますよ。
B: 妹（いもうと）さんだと思いますよ。今日は妹さんを連（つ）れてくるつもりだと言っていましたから。
 
a) What does A notice?   (Someone is sitting next to Takeshi.)
b) What information does B provide? (B thinks it is Takeshi’s younger sister.  Takeshi had told her that he planned to
bring her today.”
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/729826765441.mp3" >a) Describe the reservation A made.    
b) What question does A have?    
</question>
<answer >A: もしもし、メトロポリタンホテルです。
B: もしもし、予約(よやく）お願（ねが）いします。
A:  はい、何日からですか。
B: 来週（らいしゅう）の木曜日からツインルームを。
A: 八月四日からツインですね。はい。何日までですか。
B: 二日間泊（と）まります。
A:  はい、じゃあ、チェックアウトは六日ですね。
B: はい、アメリカンエキスプレスで払（はら）ってもいいですか。
A:  はい、結構（けっこう）です。ありがとうございます。
 
a) Describe the reservation A made.   
(She made a reservation for two nights (August 4th,
Thursday and 5th at Metropolitan Hotel.  Twin room.)
b) What question does A have?    (If she could pay with American Express)
 </answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/192427324903.mp3" >a) What is A’s initial suggestion? 
b) What is B’s response?  
</question>
<answer >  A: 次のバス停(てい）で降（お）りましょうか。
B: いや、次のバス停より、二つ目（ふたつめ）のバス停の方（ほう）が便利（べんり）ですよ。地下鉄（ちかてつ）の駅（えき）のすぐ前だから。
A:  じゃあ、そこまで行きましょう。
 
a) What is A’s initial suggestion? (Get off the bus at the next bus stop.)
b) What is B’s response?   Give
detail. (The second bus stop is more
convenient than the next one because it is right in front of the subway
station.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/91698170946.mp3" >a) What is under discussion? 
b) What changes are mentioned? What caused them? 
</question>
<answer >A: ご主人(しゅじん）はお元気（げんき）ですか。
B: ええ、ありがとうございます。元気です。でも、このごろちょっと太（ふと）りましたよ。
A: 本当（ほんとう）ですか。前は痩（や）せていましたけどねえ。
B: ええ、今は全然（ぜんぜん）運動（うんどう）しないから、ジーンズのサイズも前よりひとつ大きくなりました。
A: それはよくないですね。
 
a) What is under discussion?   (B’s husband)
b) What changes are mentioned? What caused them? (He became fat recently. His pants are one size
up now because he doesn’t exercise.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/694607717058.mp3" >a) Based on the speech styles they use, what
is the relationship between A and B? 
b) Where does this conversation most likely
take place?
c) Why are they festive? 
d) What is B’s plan for the summer? 
</question>
<answer >A: 試験（しけん）が終（お）わってよかった！
B: 本当（ほんとう）ですね。今日はゆっくり飲みましょう。 
A: そうだね。乾杯（かんぱい）！
B:乾杯！ 
A: 夏（なつ）休みはどうするつもり？
B:まだ決（き）めていませんけど、広島（ひろしま）か京都（きょうと）に旅行（りょこう）するつもりです。
A: いいねえ。
 
a) Based on the speech styles they use, what
is the relationship between A and B? 
 (A = superior/older, B =
subordinate/younger)
b) Where does this conversation most likely
take place? (In a restaurant or pub)
c) Why are they festive?    (They are
done with exams.)
d) What is B’s plan for the summer?  (Take a
trip to Hiroshima or Kyoto)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/367955749229.mp3" >a) Who is B?   
b) What is A’s assumption?
c) Is A’s assumption correct?
d) What is A concerned?  
e) How does B respond?
</question>
<answer >A: 高橋（たかはし）さんは会社まで地下鉄（ちかてつ）で来ますね。
B: いや、毎日自転車（じてんしゃ）で来ています。地下鉄より速（はや）いですから。 
A: どのくらいかかりますか。
B: ２０分ぐらいですね。
A: 寒（さむ）くないですか。
B: 冬（ふゆ）は寒いですよ。だから、手袋（てぶくろ）をして、ブーツを履（は）いてきます。
 
a) Who is B?   (Takahashi)
b) What is A’s assumption? (Takahashi comes to work by subway.)
c) Is A’s assumption correct? (No, she comes by bike because it is faster.)
d) What is A concerned?  (A wonders if it is cold.)
e) How does B respond?  (It is cold in winter. She
wears gloves and boots.) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/330296897170.mp3" >a) What does A inform B?
b) What happens around 4:30? 
c) What information does A seek? 
d) What does B say regarding to A’s question?    
e) What price is mentioned?
f) How much is it? 
</question>
<answer >A: 水曜日に韓国（かんこく）に行きますよ。
B: 何時の便（びん）ですか。
A: ええと、四時半頃（ごろ）だと思います。あのう、成田（なりた）まで電車とバスとどちらの方が速（はや）いですか。
B: 新宿（しんじゅく）から乗（の）りますか。
A: ええ。
B: 私はたいてい成田（なりた）エクスプレスで行きますよ。電車は指定席（していせき）で、乗（の）り換（か）えなくてもいいから便利（べんり）ですよ。
A: そうですか。いくらぐらいですか。
B: 片道（かたみち）三千円ぐらいだと思います。
 
a) What does A inform B?  (A is
going to Korea next Wednesday.) 
b) What happens around 4:30? (A’s flight takes off.)
c) What information does A seek? (Which is faster to get to Narita, bus or
train?
d) What does B say regarding to A’s question?    (B usually takes Narita
Express because it’s reserved seats and you don’t need to transfer.)
e) What price is mentioned? (Train ticket from Shinjyuku to Narita) 
f) How much is it?  (About three thousand yen,
one-way.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/993098245308.mp3" >a) What does A need?  Why? 
b) What question does B ask? 
c) What is A’s response? 
d) How does B respond? 
</question>
<answer >A: これを明日、会社に持（も）って行くつもりだけど、かばんか何かある？
B: うん。黒（くろ）いのと緑（みどり）のがあるけど、どっちがいい？ 
A:  緑のの方が大きくていいと思う。これ、借（か）りてもいい？
B: もちろん。私は使（つか）わないから。a) What does A need?  Why?  (She is going to bring something to the office,
and needs a bag or something)
b) What question does B ask?  (She has
black one and green one.  Which
does A prefer?)
c) What is A’s response?  (She
prefers green one because it is bigger, and asked B if she could borrow it)
d) How does B respond?  (Of course, I don’t use it.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/199328672913.mp3" >a) Where is this conversation probably taking
place?
b) What does A want to know?   
c) Does B provide the answer? 
</question>
<answer >A: すみません、横浜(よこはま）行きの電車は何番線（なんばんせん）ですか。
B: さあ、、、。改札（かいさつ）のところで聞いてください。 
 
a) Where is this conversation probably taking
place?  (At
a station.)
b) What does A want to know?   (She wants to know the track number where the
train bound for Yokohama leaves.)
c) Does B provide the answer?   (B does not know, so she told A to go ask at
the gate.)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/367275288635.mp3" >a) What does A ask? 
b) What does B tell A? 
c) What does A ask B to do? 
</question>
<answer >A: これ、どうやって書きましたか。
B: エクセルで書きました。二週間(しゅうかん）ぐらいかかりましたけど、別（べつ）に難（むず）しくなかったですよ。
A:  いつか暇（ひま）な時、教（おし）えてください。
B: ええ。いいですよ。
 
a) What does A ask?  (‘How did you write this?’)
b) What does B tell A?  (She wrote it with Excel. It
took her about two weeks but it was not difficult.)
c) What does A ask B to do? (A asked B to teach her sometime when A has a
free time.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/658206946988.mp3" >a) What did B do yesterday? With whom?
b) How was the weather? 
c) What does B ask Imada (B) to do? Why? 
d) How does A respond? 
</question>
<answer >A: きのう、どこかへ行きましたか。
B: ええ。きのうは会社の人と五時間（じかん）ぐらい野球（やきゅう）をしました。
A: 暑（あつ）くなかったですか。
B: 朝（あさ）は涼（すず）しかったですけど、午後は暑くなりましたねえ。でも、楽（たの）しかったですよ。あ、今田さんも来週（らいしゅう）来てくださいよ。来週はメンバーが二人来ないって言っていましたから。
A: 木村（きむら）さんに聞いて下さいよ。木村さんは、高校の時、チームに入っていたと言っていたから、私より上手だと思いますよ。
 
 
a) What did B do yesterday? With whom? (B played baseball with company people.)
b) How was the weather?   (Cool in the morning but got
hot in the afternoon)
c) What does B ask Imada (B) to do? Why? (‘Come next week because two members said that
they would not show up next week.’)
d) How does A respond?  (‘Please ask Kimura.  Kimura said that he belonged to a team
in high school, so I think he is better than I.’) 
 
</answer>
</exercise>
</exercises>
