<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<exercises>
<instruction>Answer the questions based on the conversation.  A refers to the first speaker, and B the second speaker. Click "Show" to see the script and answers.</instruction>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/778201677910.mp3" >a) Where is A going?  With whom? 
b) When?   
c) How is A going there?
</question>
<answer >A: 今度（こんど）のお休みには美術館（びじゅつかん）に行くつもりですか。
B: ええ、ホストファミリーと一緒（いっしょ）に行きますよ。
A:  何で行きますか。
B: お父さんが運転（うんてん）して行きたいと言っていました。
 
a) Where is A going?  With whom? (B is going to a museum with her host family.)
b) When?      (Next holiday)
c) How is A going there?  (Her host
father says he wants to drive there.) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/557410839320.mp3" >a) Who is under discussion? 
b) What news surprised B? 
 
</question>
<answer >A: きのう、川村（かわむら）さんに会いましたよ。
B: 元気（げんき）でしたか。
A:  ええ、会社を辞（や）めて、今ギターを習（なら）っているって言っていました。
B: ええっ！本当ですか？
 
a) Who is under discussion? (Kawamura)
b) What news surprised B? (That Kawamura quit company and now is studying
guitar.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/694222712730.mp3" >a) What does A ask B?
b) What is B’s response?              
</question>
<answer >A: 富士山（ふじさん）に登（のぼ）ったことがある？
B: ううん。でも、私は別（べつ）に登（のぼ）りたくないわねえ。それより、湖（みずうみ）のそばでゆっくりしたいわ。 
 a) What does A ask B?  (If B has climbed Mt. Fuji
before.)
b) What is B’s response?     
(No, but she doesn’t want to. Rather, she wants to relax by the lake.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/49944527986.mp3" >a) What comment does A make?
b) What does B suggest to do?  Why? 
</question>
<answer >A: お腹（なか）すいた。何か食べたい。
B:うん、私も。
A:どこかいいレストラン、知（し）らない？
B:駅（えき）の前の韓国（かんこく）料理は？前に友だちと行ったことがあるけど、安くておいしかったよ。
A: うん、いいよ。
 
a) What comment does A make?  (‘I am
hungry. I want to eat something’)
b) What does B suggest to do?  Why? (B
suggests that they go to a Korean restaurant in front of the station.  She has been there before with her
friend, and it was cheap and good.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/869076398740.mp3" >a) What year is B (Smith) in?
b) What is B going to do in the future? 
</question>
<answer >A: スミスさんは今何年生ですか。
B: 四年生です。 次の秋（あき）から大学院生になります。
A: 将来（しょうらい）はどうするつもりですか。
B: まだ決めていませんけど、大学院の後で、日本で働（はたら）きたいと思っています。
A: そうですか。
 
a) What year is B (Smith) in?  (B is a senior now. She is going to become a
grad student next fall.)
b) What is B going to do in the future? (She has not decided but wants to work in Japan
after graduate school.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/973265792084.mp3" >a) Why is A concerned with B? 
b) What is B’s explanation? 
c) What will happen in next month?
</question>
<answer >A: ちょっと顔（かお）が青（あお）いですけど、大丈夫（だいじょうぶ）ですか。
B: このごろ忙しくて、あまり休みを取（と）っていないからだと思います。
A:  それはよくないですねえ。
B: 来月はもっと暇（ひま）になると思うから、運動（うんどう）したり、映画（えいが）を見たりしたいですねえ。
 
a) Why is A concerned with B? (B looks pale.)
b) What is B’s explanation? (She has been busy with work and has not taken
days off lately)
c) What will happen in next month?  (B thinks
B will have more free time. She wants to do things like exercising and watching
movies then.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/91273524872.mp3" >a) What does B do on Sunday? 
b) What about A (Tanaka)?  
c) What comment does B make? 
d) How does A respond? 
</question>
<answer >A: 日曜日はいつも何をしていますか。
B: 掃除（そうじ）したり、洗濯（せんたく）したりしていますね。たいていどこにも出かけません。田中さんは？
A: 私は天気（てんき）がいい日はドライブによく行きますよ。
B: 今度（こんど）連（つ）れて行ってください。
A: ええ、ぜひ。
 
a) What does B do on Sunday?    (B does things like cleaning and doing laundry.
She usually does not go out.)
b) What about A (Tanaka)?  (She goes
for a drive on sunny days.) 
c) What comment does B make?  (‘Please
take me next time.’)
d) How does A respond?   (‘By all means.’) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/338009733081.mp3" >a) What is the topic of this conversation?
b)
What does B inform?  
</question>
<answer >A: 今の季節（きせつ）は日本ではよく雨が降（ふ）りますか
。
B: ええ、よく降りますねえ。
A: 暑(あつ）いですか。
B:暑かったり、涼（すず）しかったりしますねえ。でも、来月はすごく暑くなると思います。
  a) What is the topic of this conversation?  (Weather
in Japan at current season.)
b) What
does B inform?  (It rains a lot now. 
The temperature varies but it will get quite hot next month.) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/383405354413.mp3" >a) Where did A go on Friday? 
b) What
does B want to know?
c)
What does A tell B?
</question>
<answer >A: 金曜日にパレスホテルのパーティに行ってきましたよ。
B:そうですか。だれか有名（ゆうめい）な人がいましたか。
A:ええ、俳優（はいゆう）や歌手（かしゅ）や野球選手（やきゅうせんしゅ）も来ていて、たくさん写真（しゃしん）を撮（と）りました。
 
a) Where did A go on Friday? (Party at Palace Hotel)
b) What
does B want to know?   (B wants to know if there were any famous
people there.)
c) What
does A tell B?  (There were actors, singers and baseball players.  She took many photos.) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/256752516216.mp3" >a) Who are A and B? 
b) What does A tell B? 
c)
List two things that B ask A.
</question>
<answer >A: あさっての日本語の試験（しけん）は九時からだから、遅刻（ちこく）しないでくださいね。
B:先生、試験は二時間ですか。
A: 二時間半です。
B: 試験のあと、授業（じゅぎょう）がありますか。
A: いえ、あさっては試験だけです。
 
a) Who are A and B?   (Teacher and student)
b) What does A tell B? (The Japanese exam on the day after tomorrow starts at 9:00, and
told B not to be late.)
c) List two things that B ask A. (How long is the exam?  Is there a class after the exam?)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/455069426520.mp3" >a) Who are A and B? 
b) What does A tell B? Why? 
c) What permission does A seek? 
d)
Does A give the permission?
</question>
<answer >A: 今晩はテレビを見たり、音楽（おんがく）を聴（き）いたりしてはいけませんよ。
B: どうして？
A: お父さんの会社の人が来るから。
B:分かった。部屋（へや）でおもちゃで遊（あそ）んでもいい？
A:勉強（べんきょう）の後でね。
B:は〜い。
 
a) Who are A and B?   (A= Mother, B= child)
b) What does A tell B? Why?  (B should
not watch TV or listen to music tonight. Because someone from Father’s company
will visit.)
c) What permission does A seek?  (She
wants to play with toys in her room.)
d) Does A give the permission?  (‘Yes,
after studying’)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >a) What does A urge B to eat? 
b) How does A acquire them? Give details. 
c) What is B’s initial response to the offer? 
d) How does A react?   
e)
What is B’s response? 
</question>
<answer >A: このお菓子（かし）、食べませんか。さっき、田中さんからもらいましたけど、おいしいですよ。田中さんのおばあさんが作ったって言っていました。
B: あ、ありがとうございます。じゃあ、一つだけ。
A:もっと、どうぞ。たくさん食べてください。
B:いや、私、今ダイエットしていますから、、。 
 a) What does A urge B to eat?  (Sweets.
)
b) How does A acquire them? Give details. (She got them from Tanaka.  Tanaka’s grandmother made them.)
c) What is B’s initial response to the offer? (‘Thank you. I will have one.’)
d) How does A react?   (A urged B to ear more.)
e) What is B’s response?    (‘I am on a diet now.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/287866669082.mp3" >a) What is the weather like today? 
b) What
does A invite B to do? 
c)
What is B going to do?  Why?    
</question>
<answer >A: 今日はすごく暖（あたた）かいね。
B:うん。いい天気だね。
A:次の授業（じゅぎょう）をサボって、遊（あそ）びに行かない？
B:私、先週も病気（びょうき）だと言って、うそをついて休んだから、今日は授業に出るわ。
A: あ、そう。
 
a) What is the weather like today?  (Very
warm and nice.)
b) What
does A invite B to do? (They should cut
the next class and go have  fun.)
c) What
is B going to do?  Why?    (She is going to attend the
class.  She missed the class last
week.  She told that she was sick,
which was a lie.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/207474047158.mp3" >a) Where does this conversation take place? 
b) What is B looking for?
c) What does A recommend?
d)
What does B purchase?  How many?
</question>
<answer >A: いらっしゃいませ。
B:お土産（みやげ）に何か食べ物を買いたいと思ってねえ。A: このお菓子（かし）はどうですか。北海道（ほっかいどう）のお土産にいいですよ。
B: そうですね。じゃあ、六つください。
A: ありがとうございます。
 
a) Where does this conversation take place?   (At a store in Hokkaido)
b) What is B looking for?   (B wants to buy food as a souvenir.)
c) What does A recommend?  (Sweets.)
d) What does B purchase?  How many? (B buys what A recommended. 
Six of them.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/848101819473.mp3" >a) Where is B going?  When? Give details. 
b) What does B’s wife want to do?  
c)
What is the reason why A doesn’t comply with her wishes?    
</question>
<answer >A: お正月（しょうがつ）はどちらへ？
B: 母に会いに行くつもりです。
A: お母さんはどちらに住んでいますか。
B: 九州（きゅうしゅう）です。
A: 奥（おく）さんもご一緒（いっしょ）ですか。
B: ええ。でも、家内（かない）は暖（あたた）かいところに行きたがっていますけど、、、。
A: 九州は暖かいでしょう？
B: いや、九州よりもっと暖かいところですよ。ハワイや沖縄（おきなわ）だと思いますけど、家にはお金がないですから。
 
a) Where is B going?  When? Give details. (Go
to see his mother in Kyusyuu on New Year.)
b) What does B’s wife want to do?  (She
wants to go to a warmer place like Hawaii or Okinawa.)
c) What is the reason why A doesn’t comply
with her wishes?    (They
don’t have money.)  
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/490412992033.mp3" >a) Why is does A want to do? 
b) How does A describe his friend?
c) How old is A’s friend? 
d)
What does Yukari decide in the end?  
</question>
<answer >A: ゆかりさん、ゆかりさんを友だちに紹介（しょうかい）したいと思ってるけど、今日、時間ある？
B: どんな人ですか？
A: 北海道（ほっかいどう）出身（しゅっしん）で、社長（しゃちょう）だよ。まあ、会社はあまり大きくないけど。大きい夢(ゆめ）を持っている人だと思うよ。
B: ふうん。その人、今何歳（さい）ですか。
A: 僕（ぼく）より五歳ぐらい上だと思うけど。
B: そうですねえ。
A: どう？その人はぜひ会いたいと言っているけど。
B: 分かりました。じゃあ。
A: ああ、よかった！
 
a) Why is does A want to do? (Introduce Yukari to his friend.)
b) How does A describe his friend?  (He is
from Hokkaido. He is a company president, though it is not a big company.  He has a big dream.)
c) How old is A’s friend?  (Three
year older than A.)
d) What does Yukari decide in the end?  (She
agreed to meet him.)
</answer>
</exercise>
</exercises>
