<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<exercises>
<instruction>What would you say in the following situations?  Record your answers and check them against the models.</instruction>
<exercise>
<question  >Inform that you are married, and have two children.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/950483658890.mp3">結婚けっこんしています。そして、子供こどもが二人ふたりいます。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that your father and mother live in Boston.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/955001355921.mp3">父ちちと母はははボストンに住すんでいます。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your colleague asked you to describe how your older sister looks.  Tell him/her that she is thin and very
tall.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/405936475451.mp3">やせていて、とても背せが高たかいです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your teacher said you looked sleepy today. Tell your
teacher that you didn’t sleep because you were playing computer game (all
night).
</question>
<answer audio="audio/434243642565.mp3">昨日きのう（は）寝ねませんでした。コンピュータゲームをしていましたから。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You went to a new Japanese restaurant yesterday.  Tell your colleague that the food was very delicious and
inexpensive.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/393907215752.mp3">とてもおいしくて安やすかったです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You just finished your work. 
Invite your colleagues for dinner at a restaurant if he/she likes.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/462967552783.mp3">よかったら、レストランに晩ばんご飯はんを食たべに行いきませんか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask what your colleague was doing around 7pm yesterday.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/839828309443.mp3">きのうの午後ごご七時ごろ何なにをしていましたか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your colleague if his/her older brother works for a company.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/677242017424.mp3">お兄にいさんは会社かいしゃに勤つとめていますか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You now have a new girlfriend. Inform your colleague that she (your
girlfriend) is a pretty and very kind person.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/560652301953.mp3">きれいでとても親切しんせつな人です。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You and your colleague are looking at your photo.  Tell him/her that you didn’t wear glasses when you were a
college student.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/446974456849.mp3">大学生の時はめがねをかけていませんでした。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You invited your neighbor for having coffee at your house.  Your neighbor asked if she could bring
her sister.  Tell your neighbor
that she, of course, can bring (her).
</question>
<answer audio="audio/30657279844.mp3">もちろん。／もちろん連つれて来きてもいいですよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask if your colleague’s younger sister knows Japanese songs.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/617600445243.mp3">妹いもうとさんは日本の歌うたを知しっていますか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You
come to a company cafeteria to have a coffee with your colleague, and notice
that a beautiful woman is drinking a coffee alone over there.  She has big eyes and long hair.  Describe the situation and the person,
and ask your colleague who that is.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/210165475336.mp3">きれいな女の人が一人でコーヒーを飲んでいますね。目めが大きくて、髪かみが長ながい女の人です。あの人はだれですか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your colleague asked you about the person from Spain.  Tell her that you don’t know her. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/511723089804.mp3">いいえ、知しりません。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Inform your colleague that you didn’t eat anything in the morning.
</question>
<answer >朝あさ、何なにも食べませんでした。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your neighbor asked what you will do this weekend.  Inform that you will not do anything in
particular.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/635590166392.mp3">別べつに何なにもしません。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You are at a cafeteria and see your classmate eating alone.  Go there and ask if you could sit
(here) and eat together.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/719052593297.mp3">ここに座すわって、いっしょに食べてもいいですか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You know that your teacher has siblings, but you don’t know how many.  Ask how many she has.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/914616871466.mp3">兄弟きょうだいが何人なんにんいますか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that Mr. Tanaka always
wears T-shirt.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/12137075959.mp3">田中たなかさんはいつもＴシャツを着きていますね。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your teacher asked what you did on Sunday.  Tell her that you went to see a movie
with your friend, had dinner at a restaurant, and then went home around 11pm.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/528075554481.mp3">日曜日に友達ともだちと映画えいがを見に行って、レストランで晩ばんご飯はんを食べて、十一時ごろ家うちに帰りました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You colleague asked you about Ms. Yamada’s older
brother, who is a mutual acquaintance. 
Tell him that Ms. Yamada’s older brother went to China to teach Japanese
two years ago, and returned to Japan last week.  He stayed with Chinese family, so he understands Chinese
very well.
 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/212429539141.mp3">山田さんのお兄にいさんはおととし中国に日本語を教おしえに行って、先週せんしゅう帰りました。中国人の家族かぞくと住すんでいましたから、中国語がよくわかります。</answer>
</exercise>
</exercises>
