<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<exercises>
<instruction>What would you say in the following situations?  Record your answers and check them against the models.</instruction>
<exercise>
<question  >Your father told you that he often spent time pleasantly with his friends
when he was a college student.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/555965689550.mp3">父は大学生の時よく友達ともだちと遊あそんだと言っていました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Find out who the person wearing a pair of jeans and red T-shirt is.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/478887917314.mp3">ジーンズをはいて、赤あかいＴシャツを着きている人はだれですか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your classmate that you haven’t eaten anything yet.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/764634645384.mp3">まだ何も食べていない。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that Mr. Suzuki had told you that he was not healthy
yesterday.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/392039600134.mp3">鈴木すずきさんはきのう元気げんきじゃなかったと言いました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your friend that you heard that Kyoko had a date with Makoto, although
Kyoko said that she didn’t go out on weekend. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/310044191851.mp3">京子きょうこさんは週末しゅうまつ出かけなかったと言」ったけど、まことさんとデートしたと聞きいたよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your acquaintance that Tanaka told you that he didn’t have a lot of
free time last week.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/121901104766.mp3">田中さんは先週せんしゅうひまじゃなかったと言っていました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your friend that you got two tickets to a concert from Mr. Yoshida.  Invite your friend to go with you.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/109199383136.mp3">吉田よしださんにコンサートの切符きっぷを２枚まいもらったから、いっしょに行かない？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your classmate if she had already written the Japanese composition.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/388199125257.mp3">もう日本語の作文さくぶんを書いた？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask
your friend if he finished the economics homework.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/980148658928.mp3">経済けいざいの宿題しゅくだい、終おわった？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You friend told you that she saw a new movie, and it was very
interesting.   Tell your
colleague what your friend told you.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/548646221709.mp3">友だちが新あたらしい映画えいがを見て、とてもおもしろかったと言っていました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You are at a concession stand in the movie theater.  Buy two coffees.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/890838485284.mp3">コーヒーを二つください。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tanaka
told you that she took a walk for about one hour in the morning and went to see
her family around 4pm on Sunday. Report another colleague what Tanaka did.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/78203356432.mp3">日曜日は朝一時間ぐらい散歩さんぽをして、午後四時ごろ家族かぞくに会あいに行ったと言いました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your acquaintance that you think that the weather was not good in
Tokyo last week. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/133013204977.mp3">先週せんしゅう東京とうきょうは天気てんきがよくなかったと思います。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >One
of your classmates wants to know who likes dogs.  Tell him that you think the person who likes dogs is Tom.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/597152722141.mp3">犬いぬが好すきな人はトムさんだと思うよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your colleague asks you what sport is popular in Japan.  Tell him that you think that soccer is
popular.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/151804258654.mp3">サッカーが人気にんきがあると思います。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your colleague asked you about what Mary looks like.  Tell him that Mary has blue eyes and
she is tall. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/968231548628.mp3">メアリーさんは目めが青あおくて、とても背せが高いです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that you
went to see a Chinese movie with the person who is studying Chinese.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/815352628779.mp3">中国語ちゅうごくごを勉強べんきょうしている人ひとと中国ちゅうごくの映画えいがを見みに行いきました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your friend that you went to a department store and bought one black coat and
two light blue T-shirts.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/364419406120.mp3">デパートに行いって、黒くろいコートと水色みずいろのＴシャツを２枚まい買かった。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You were talking about your childhood with your friend.  Tell her that you were an energetic child but your younger brother was quiet. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/230140709391.mp3">私は元気げんきな子どもだったけど、弟おとうとは静しずかだった。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your colleague if she knows the name of the person who is sitting over
there.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/877362234824.mp3">あそこで座すわっている人の名前を知っていますか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your colleague asked you if you have already purchased a Shinkansen
ticket.  Tell her that you have not
purchased one yet because you have been very busy this week. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/906210979753.mp3">今週こんしゅうは忙いそがしかったから、まだ買かっていません。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your colleague if she doesn't like people who smoke.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/752180963362.mp3">たばこを吸すう人は好きじゃないですか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your friend asked you what you got on your birthday.  Tell him that you received a white dress from your mother last year. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/310067646744.mp3">去年きょねんは母に白いドレスをもらったよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your friend if all (people) came to the ski trip last month.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/13232594196.mp3">先月のスキーの旅行りょこうにみんな来た？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You are talking about your father with your colleague.  Tell your colleague that he said that he did not play sports much when he was young. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/25535558424.mp3">父は若わかい時、あまりスポーツをしなかったと言っていました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You are telling your colleague about your life in a foreign country.  Tell her that you were very lonely. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/254658789447.mp3">とても寂さびしかったです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You talking with a colleague about Tanaka. Tell him that Tanaka is sick but he has not taken medicine yet. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/335819725719.mp3">田中さんは病気びょうきですけど、薬くすりはまだ飲んでいません。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your mother that you didn't receive anything from your teacher today.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/801943613289.mp3">今日、先生に何ももらわなかったよ。</answer>
</exercise>
</exercises>
