<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<exercises>
<instruction>What would you say in the following situations?  Record your answers and check them against the models.</instruction>
<exercise>
<question  >You
colleague asks you why you want to leave the office early.  Explain it is that you have a fever and
cough.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/46598051981.mp3">熱ねるがあって、咳せきが出るんです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You colleague looks very tired and you are concerned.  Ask what happened to her.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/448238409663.mp3">どうしたんですか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You
went to a department store to buy a new dress.  You found one you like, but you didn't buy it because it was
too expensive.  Explain your friend
why you didn't buy it.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/437359387594.mp3">高すぎたから、買わなかったんだ。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
colleague caught a cold and was absent from work yesterday.  He comes to work today, but he is still
sick.  Give him advice to drink
orange juice everyday.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/679597080758.mp3">毎日オレンジジュースを飲んだほうがいいですよ。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
colleague likes drinking and tends to drink too much.  Give him advice not drink too much.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/888726747901.mp3">飲みすぎないほうがいいですよ。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
friend is concerned because you look depressed.  Explain it is that you just broke up with your boyfriend.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/221733757601.mp3">彼かれと別わかれたんだ。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask
you acquaintance what she is interested in. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/160491776027.mp3">何に興味きょうみがありますか。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You
are not feeling well, and come to see a doctor.  Explain it is that you have a headache and sore throat.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/833248192285.mp3">頭あたまが痛いたくて、喉のども痛いたいんです。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your teacher that you didn’t do homework because he was sick.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/385120977022.mp3">病気だったので、宿題しゅくだいをしませんでした。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >It
is midnight now.  Your friend wants
to play a computer game with you. 
Decline his invitation by explaining it is that you must wake up early
tomorrow morning. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/736707190125.mp3">明日あしたは朝早はやく起おきなければ／起おきなきゃいけないんだ。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You
were asked what kind of person Keiko is. 
Tell your colleague that she is very popular because she is smart and
pretty.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/372846057712.mp3">けいこさんは頭あたまがよくて、きれいなので、とても人気があります。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask
your colleague why he was absent from work yesterday.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/195650416267.mp3">どうして昨日きのう仕事を休んだんですか。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You
were invited to a dinner at your boss’s house, but you already have a plan.
Explain it is that you have a scheduling conflict.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/933375713721.mp3">すみません。都合つごうが悪わるいんです。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
colleague asked why you decided to marry Yamada.  Explain it is that he is a smart and very kind person.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/116232811779.mp3">頭あたまがよくてとても優やさしい人なんです。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
acquaintance is sick. Tell him to take care. Wish his swift recovery.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/810185400144.mp3">お大事だいじに。／早くよくなってください。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your neighbor that it will be probably not very cold tomorrow.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/6099097970.mp3">明日はあまり寒さむくないでしょう。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your colleague that Keiko’s boyfriend is probably an office worker.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/771770143489.mp3">けいこさんの彼かれは、多分たぶん会社員でしょう。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >A
group of your colleagues went to camping last weekend.   Tell your boss that you think
that Yamada, one of your colleagues, probably didn’t go because
she doesn’t like outdoor activities [‘autodoa’ in katakana].  
</question>
<answer audio="audio/643797991172.mp3">田中さんはアウトドアが好きじゃないので、多分たぶん、先週の週末しゅうまつキャンプに行かなかっただろうと思います。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
colleague asked you how Tanaka, another colleague, gave his speech the other
day. Tell him that Tanaka had told you that he was nervous, because he had to
speak in English.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/165953434378.mp3">田中さんは英語で話さなければ／話さなきゃいけなかったので、緊張きんちょうしたと言っていました。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your friend that your grade of Economics class this semester was terrible.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/611038624615.mp3">今学期きの経済けいざいの成績せいせきはすごく悪わるかった。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
colleague asked you about your father’s trip to America in the near
future.  Tell your colleague that
your father has never been to foreign countries before, so you are worried.  
</question>
<answer audio="audio/821507146422.mp3">父は外国に行ったことがないので、心配しんぱいしています。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your roommate that you think it is probably going to be about 30C (95F) degrees
today.  Advise her that she should
stay in cool place as much as possible.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/221490954821.mp3">今日は多分たぶん３０度どぐらいになると思うよ。できるだけ涼すずしい所ところにいたほうがいいよ。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your female colleague that your wife’s birthday is coming up.  Tell her (it is that) you want to buy
something fantastic and ask her what would be good as a present. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/550281309130.mp3">もうすぐ家内かないの誕生日たんじょうびです。何か素敵すてきな物ものを買いたいんですが、プレゼントに何がいいでしょうか。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your colleague asked you what she should wear when she goes to a soccer game.  Tell her that she should wear a winter coat because they said that it would become snowy weather this afternoon.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/149256687917.mp3">今日の午後、雪になると言っていたから、冬のコートを着きて行ったほうがいいですよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your colleague told you that she would take a bus to Tanaka's office.  Tell her that it would be better if she took a subway to Kyoto Station and walk from there. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/128250126800.mp3">地下鉄ちかてつで京都と駅えきまで行って、そこから歩あるいたほうがいいですよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your teacher to teach you the meaning of this word in English. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/4005592157.mp3">この単語たんごの意味いみを英語で教おしえてください。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your friend why she broke up with your boyfriend. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/367518784086.mp3">どうして彼かれと別わかれたの？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your colleague did not come to the meeting.  Ask him he had some business to take care of.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/272067717117.mp3">用事ようじがあったんですか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your roommate who is about to leave that the weather forecast said that it would be cloudy or rain tonight so she should bring an umbrella with her. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/773287738747.mp3">天気予報よほうは今晩くもりか雨だと言っていたから、傘かさを持って行ったほうがいいよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your supervisor if you have to come early tomorrow.  
</question>
<answer audio="audio/151549698392.mp3">あしたの朝、早く来なければいけませんか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your acquaintance asked you if you went to the store yesterday.  Tell him that you didn't because yesterday was a holiday. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/319912355466.mp3">きのうは休みだったので、行きませんでした。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your acquaintance asked you if it was sunny in Osaka yesterday.  Tell him that it probably was cloudy.  
</question>
<answer audio="audio/238926440783.mp3">多分たぶん曇くもりだったでしょう。</answer>
</exercise>
</exercises>
