<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<exercises>
<instruction>What would you say in the following situations?  Record your answers and check them against the models.</instruction>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your friend which is taller, Keiko or Yuko.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/524001684811.mp3">けいこさんとゆうこさんとどっちの方ほうが背せが高い？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your colleague that Takashi is better at singing songs than Robert.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/502562089431.mp3">たかしさんの方ほうがロバートさんより歌うたが上手じょうずです。／歌うたを歌うたうのが上手じょうずです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
that (going by) airplane is the fastest from Tokyo to Osaka among airplanes,
bullet trains and buses, but it is most expensive.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/383087457697.mp3">東京から大阪おおさかまで飛行機ひこうきと新幹線しんかんせんとバスの中で、飛行機ひこうきが一番いちばん速はやいですが、一番いちばん高たかいです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask
your friend which he likes best, Japanese food, Chinese food and Italian food.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/999326196107.mp3">日本料理りょうりと中華料理ちゅうかりょうりとイタリア料理りょうりの中なかでどれが一番いちばん好き？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your colleague what she likes best among sports.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/386954047325.mp3">スポーツの中で何が一番いちばん好きですか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your classmate who has the longest hair in class.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/944828096385.mp3">クラスの中でだれが一番いちばん髪かみ長いですか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
friend wants to buy a new sweater. 
You are asked which looks better on her, red one or blue one.   Tell her that the blue one is
better.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/697116877491.mp3">赤あかいのより青あおい方ほうがいいよ。／赤あかいのより青あおいのの方ほうがいいよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You found a Japanese textbook on the desk after class.  Pick it up and ask your classmate whose
this is.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/458490836274.mp3">これはだれのですか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that you intend to stay your friend's house this
weekend.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/6865897755.mp3">週末しゅうまつ友だちの家に泊とまるつもりです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
colleague told you that he intends not to go out tomorrow.  Report what he told you to other
colleague.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/686992311458.mp3">明日あした出でかけないつもりだと言いっていました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >It became very warm these days. 
Describe the change.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/109661056500.mp3">このごろとても暖あたたかくなりましたね。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your friend that you intend to become a doctor, so you are studying a
lot.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/59571798033.mp3">医者いしゃになるつもりだから、たくさん勉強べんきょうしています。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask
your colleague if he has been to anywhere last night.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/433803073902.mp3">きのうの夜どこかに行きましたか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You are chatting with your acquaintance over the Internet. Write to her
that it was very cold and snowed yesterday.  Therefore, you didn't go anywhere.  You read books and watched TV at home.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/385111780212.mp3">きのうはとても寒さむくて、雪が降ふりました。だから、どこにも行きませんでした。家で本を読んで、テレビを見ました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your friend that it took one hour by bus from your home to hospital.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/876106106517.mp3">家から病院びょういんまでバスで一時間かかった。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your colleague that your room became very clean because you cleaned it.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/586193666867.mp3">掃除そうじしたから、部屋へやがきれいになりました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask a store clerk if you can pay with a credit card.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/243403288609.mp3">クレジットカードで払はらってもいいですか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You are at an apartment with your real estate agent.  Ask her how long it takes to university
on foot.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/182896008090.mp3">大学まで歩あるいてどのぐらいかかりますか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your classmate that you will go to study in Japan in one month, and that you
intend to be in Japan for six months.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/519144650389.mp3">一ヶ月後に日本に勉強しに行きます。六ヶ月日本にいるつもりです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that you talk in English with your father but in
Spanish with your mother. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/18241452359.mp3">父とはフランス語で話しますけど、母とはスペイン語ごで話します。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Comment to your colleague that this town has become livelier than before. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/806497707803.mp3">この町は前よりにぎやかになりましたねえ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your friend that your baggage is bigger than Mary’s.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/530096455783.mp3">私の荷物にもつの方ほうがメアリーさんのより大きいよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that you think Suzuki came to the office earlier than
Tanaka did today.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/436260552917.mp3">今日は鈴木すずきさんの方ほうが田中さんより早はやく会社に来たと思います。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your friend who is studying Japanese which she thinks easier between reading and speaking.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/314188555189.mp3">読むのと話すのと、どっちの方が簡単かんたんだと思う？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your friend asks you if you still speak French.  Tell her that you become not speak French these days.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/825416172229.mp3">このごろフランス語を話さなくなりました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your colleague asks you if you plan to do anything this weekend.  Tell him that you plan to go somewhere.
</question>
<answer >どこかに行くつもりですよ。</answer>
</exercise>
</exercises>
