<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<exercises>
<instruction>What would you say in the following situations?  Record your answers and check them against the models.</instruction>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that you think that Boston is a very lively town.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/99865338373.mp3">ボストンはとてもにぎやかな町まちだと思います。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
friend asked you about Yamamoto. Tell your friend that Yamamoto had said that
she would go shopping in New York this weekend.  
</question>
<answer audio="audio/149092143475.mp3">山本さんは週末しゅうまつニューヨークに買かい物ものをしに行くと言っていた。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You
are working at a museum. You noticed that a visitor is taking a picture.  Request not to take a picture.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/728233180780.mp3">写真しゃしんを撮とらないでください。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your friend if he cooks often.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/656167435300.mp3">よく料理りょうりする？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your American colleague what he thinks of Japanese foods.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/656978772095.mp3">日本の食べ物ものについて、どう思いますか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your colleague that Keiko's room is always clean, but that she told you that
she doesn't clean her room everyday.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/811910906647.mp3">けいこさんの部屋へやはとてもきれいですが、毎日掃除そうじしないと言っていました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that you think that Japanese is not difficult, but that
Mary thinks that it is difficult.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/457256411974.mp3">日本語はむずかしくないと思いますが、メアリーさんは「むずかしいと思っています。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You
saw your neighbor while you jogged jog in the morning.  She asked you if it would rain
today.  Tell her that it will not
rain according to the weather forecast.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/311094899735.mp3">天気予報てんきよほうで今日雨あめが降ふらないと言っていましたよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your friend if she has a test in political science class tomorrow.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/923119568339.mp3">明日あした、政治せいじのクラスのテストがある？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your friend that you like cooking, but you are not good at it.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/469959549679.mp3">料理りょうりするのが好すきだけど、上手じょうずじゃない。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask
your colleague if he will bring something to Keiko’s birthday party.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/89870344222.mp3">けいこさんの誕生日たんじょうびパーティに何か持もって行きますか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that you didn’t do anything yesterday, so it was very
boring.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/687725287470.mp3">きのうは何もしませんでしたから、とてもつまらなかったです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You don't want your colleague to call you late at night.  Ask her not to call you late at night.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/469277473473.mp3">夜遅おそく電話でんわをかけないでください。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You
heard that one of your office workers went to New York by car this weekend, but
you don’t know who drove.  Find out
who did.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/608841772963.mp3">だれが車を運転うんてんしましたか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You were invited to a barbecue party at your friend's house.  You heard that one of your friends
would not be able to come because he has a part-time job.  Express your disappointment. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/364395002908.mp3">残念ざんねんだねえ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your colleague, Keiko, thinks that Mary speaks Japanese very well.  Agree with Keiko.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/81179974907.mp3">私わたしもそう思います。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
colleague asked you about Kimura, who is your friend. Tell your colleague that
Kimura had told you that she often goes swimming at the pool because she likes
swimming.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/274432292281.mp3">泳およぐのが好すきだから、よくプールに泳およぎに行くと言いました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
classmate is taking five classes. 
Ask which class is interesting.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/740135795976.mp3">どのクラスがおもしろい？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You
heard that your neighbor likes playing tennis.  Tell him that you are bad at playing tennis, but you like
tennis, too. Invite him to play on Sunday.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/515733095658.mp3">テニスをするのが下手へたですが、好すきです。日曜日に｜いっしょにテニスをしませんか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/252325926049.mp3" >Tell your friend that you don't like to go see a movie alone. 
</question>
<answer audio="audio/877138917640.mp3">一人で映画えいがを見に行くのは好すきじゃないよ。</answer>
</exercise>
</exercises>
