<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<exercises>
<instruction>What would you say in the following situations?  Record your answers and check them against the models.</instruction>
<exercise>
<question  >Comment
to your classmate that he is good at playing guitar.  And, tell him that you want to learn (playing) guitar.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/225926811182.mp3">ギターを弾ひくのが上手ですね。ギターが習ならいたいです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your colleague that you wanted to stay at your friend's house when you were
child on every Saturday.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/251809067865.mp3">子供こどもの時、毎週土曜日に友達ともだちの家に泊とまりたかったです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that you intend to go to Mr. Fuji next weekend because
your friend wants to climb Mt. Fuji.  
</question>
<answer audio="audio/232533663817.mp3">友達だちが富士山ふじさんに登のぼりたがっているから、来週の週末富士山ふじさんに行くつもりです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that you usually do such things as shopping and doing
laundry on Monday.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/537426835931.mp3">たいてい月曜日に買い物ものしたり洗濯せんたくしたりします。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask
your friend where she is coming from.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/542679567429.mp3">出身しゅっしんはどこ？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You meet your acquaintance that you haven't seen for a long time.  Greet him politely.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/78234097994.mp3">久ひさしぶりですね。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your neighbor that you have met Mr. Bill Gates（ビル・ゲイツ）and he has told you that
he likes baseball.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/120542907462.mp3">ビル・ゲイツに会あったことがあります。野球やきゅうが好すきだと言いっていました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your classmate that you have never cut classes.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/839890693388.mp3">授業じゅぎょうをサボったことはないよ。
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
friend invites you for dinner.  She
suggests Japanese food, but you had Japanese food for dinner last night.  Tell her that you had sushi for dinner
yesterday and suggest Italian food instead.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/411845679468.mp3">昨日きのう晩ばんご飯はんにおすしを食べたから、イタリア料理りょうりはどう？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your neighbor that you drink tea and coffee, for example, but you don't drink
Japanese tea.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/976956803425.mp3">紅茶こうちゃやコーヒーは飲みますが、日本のお茶ちゃは飲みません。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your friend that you bought just one T-shirt because you didn’t have much
money.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/573439290587.mp3">お金をあまり持っていなかったから、Ｔシャツを一枚まいだけ買いました。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You
heard that your friend would go to Australia in July.  Tell her that you have never been there and also want to go
there.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/158407659110.mp3">オーストラリアに行ったことがないから、私も行きたい。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your colleague that you think that Mr. Tanaka likes doing such things as going
for a drive and singing karaoke on weekend.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/34020050968.mp3">田中さんは週末ドライブをしたり、カラオケをしたりするのが好きだと思います。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You were asked what you want to do during summer vacation.  Tell your friend that you want to do
such things like doing a part-time job and playing with friends.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/290597851927.mp3">アルバイトをしたり、友達ともだちと遊あそんだりしたい。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your colleague that Yamashita wanted to go dancing, but he didn’t go
because he had a lot of work.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/748484546392.mp3">山下さんは踊おどりに行きたがっていましたが、たくさん仕事があったから、行きませんでした。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your neighbor if he has had a fight with a friend.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/683514202785.mp3">友達ともだちとけんかをしたことがありますか。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You
went to see a news movie on weekend.  Tell your friend that it was so-so.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/868852232889.mp3">まあまあだったよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell
your teacher that you are studying for about five hours every day because you
want to be a president of a company in the future.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/588021342250.mp3">将来しょうらい社長になりたいから、毎日五時間ぐらい勉強しています。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
acquaintance plans to go to Japan next year and asks you about Kyoto and
Tokyo.  Tell her that there are
many famous temples in Kyoto, but there are not many in Tokyo.
</question>
<answer audio="audio/192944979135.mp3">京都きょうとにはたくさん有名ゆうめいなお寺てらがありますが、東京にはあまりありませんよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your
American friend asked you what he should bring when he visits people in
Japan.  Tell him that you think
that things like sweets and fruits are good for souvenir.  
</question>
<answer audio="audio/700685764270.mp3">おみやげにはお菓子かしや果物くだものがいいと思うよ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your friend which is better between swimming in the lake and  going art museum. 
</question>
<answer >湖みずうみで泳およぐのと美術館びじゅつかんに行くのとどっちがいい？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Your teacher asked you what you want to do in the future.  Tell her that you want to become either a singer or a actress in the future. 
</question>
<answer >将来しょうらい、歌手か女優ゆうになりたいです。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Tell your child that he must not do things like telling a lie or cutting classes. 
</question>
<answer >うそをついたり、授業じゅぎょうをサボったりしてはいけません。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your colleague to introduce the president of your his older brother's company to you.
</question>
<answer >お兄さんの会社の社長さんを私に紹介しょうかいしてください。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >Ask your friend if he has ever be late for his class.
</question>
<answer >授業じゅぎょうに遅刻ちこくしたことがある？</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You are staying in Okinawa with friends. Tell them, expecting agreement, that you want to stay here for one more week.  
</question>
<answer audio="audio/764079323577.mp3">もう一週間、ここにいたいねえ。</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >You are on Shinkansen with your colleague.  Tell him that you are a bit thirsty.  
</question>
<answer audio="audio/681361975920.mp3">ちょっと、のどが渇かわきました。</answer>
</exercise>
</exercises>
