<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<exercises>
<instruction> Answer the questions based on the conversation.  A refers to the first speaker, B the second.  Click "Show" for the scripts and the answers. </instruction>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/304120170259.mp3" >a) How many siblings does B have? 
b) What do they do?
</question>
<answer >A: ご兄弟(きょうだい）はいますか。
B: はい、兄（あに）と姉（あね）がいます。
A:お兄（にい）さんも東京にいますか。
B:いいえ、兄（あに）は神戸（こうべ）の会社に勤めています。姉（あね）は東京の高校（こうこう）で英語（えいご）を教（おし）えています。
 
a) How many siblings does B have?  (An older brother and an older sister.)
b) What do they do?   (Older brother is working for
a company in Kobe. Older sister is teaching English at a high school in Tokyo.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/259330843648.mp3" >a) What is A concerned?  
b) What is B’s response? 
</question>
<answer >A: この会社（かいしゃ）ではジーンズをはいてもいいですか。 B: そうですね、、、それはちょっと。
A: 分かりました。
 
a) What is A concerned?   (Whether it is allowed to wear jeans in the office)
b) What is B’s response?   (‘Well, it’s a bit (problem).” )
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/236749822347.mp3" >a) What is the topic of the conversation? 
b) What is B’s opinion on it? 
</question>
<answer >A: 新(あたら）しいアパートはどうですか。
B: 窓（まど）が大きくて、とてもいいですよ。それに、バス停（てい）がすぐ前（まえ）で便利（べんり）です。
 
a) What is the topic of the conversation?  (B’s new
apartment)
b) What is B’s opinion on it?  (Windows
are big, so it’s nice. 
Furthermore, the bus stop is right in front, so it is convenient)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/896579691981.mp3" >a) What does A notice? 
b) What does A assume?   
c) What is the actual situation?
</question>
<answer >A: あ、佐藤(さとう）さんがいませんね。 
B: ええ。
A: 今日はお休（やす）みですか。
B: いや、今コンビニに昼（ひる）ご飯（はん）を買（か）いに行っていますよ。
 
a) What does A notice?  (Satoo is not there.)
b) What does A assume?   (It is Satoo’s day
off.)
c) What is the actual situation? (Satoo went to a convenience store to buy lunch.) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/690627953809.mp3" >a) Who is being discussed? 
b) Where is the person?  Why? 
c) Who else is mentioned in the conversation?
Describe the person. 
d) What happened in August?   
</question>
<answer >A: お姉(ねえ）さんと一緒（いっしょ）に住（す）んでいますか。
B: いえ、姉（あね）は結婚（けっこん）して、今はシドニーにいますよ。
A:そうですか。お子（こ）さんもいますか。 B:ええ、女の子です。今２歳（さい）で、目（め）が大きくてかわいいですよ。
A: よくオーストラリアに行きますか。
B:いいえ、でも、八月に姉（あね）の家族（かぞく）に会（あ）いに行ってきました 。楽（たの）しかったですよ。
 
a) Who is being discussed?  (B’s older sister.)
b) Where is the person?  Why? (She is married
and is now in Sydney.)
c) Who else is mentioned in the conversation?
Describe the person.  (A daughter
of B’s older sister is mentioned. She is two years old, and cute with big eyes.
)
d) What happened in August?    (B went to see her older
sister’s family. It was fun.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/745089228571.mp3" >a) Who is A looking for?
b) What is the person doing?  Where? 
</question>
<answer >A: みちこさんはどこにいますか。
B: みちこさんですか。ここにいますよ。
A:どこですか。
B: 窓(まど）のそばで教科書（きょうかしょ）を読（よ）んでいますよ。
 
a) Who is A looking for?    (Michiko)
b) What is the person doing?  Where?  (She is reading her textbook near the window.)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/342106068813.mp3" >a) Who is Michelle? 
b) Does A know Michelle well?  
c) What does A think of Michelle?  
d) What does B think of her? 
</question>
<answer >A: あの留学生(りゅうがくせい）の名前（なまえ）を知（し）っていますか。
B: ミシェルさんです。
A: 背（せ）が高（たか）くて、髪（かみ）がきれいで、かっこいいですね。
B:ええ、それにとても頭（あたま）がいいですよ。
 
a) Who is Michelle?  (An exchange student)
b) Does A know Michelle well?   (Apparently
no. She didn’t know her name.)
c) What does A think of Michelle?  (She is
tall, has beautiful hair and cool) 
d) What does B think of her?  (She is
very smart.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/323578121679.mp3" >a) Who are in Canada? 
b) Describe the living condition of the
person.   
 
</question>
<answer >A: お国(くに）はどちらですか。
B: 私（わたし）は台湾（たいわん）から来（き）ました。でも、父（ちち）はカナダに住（す）んでいます。
A:カナダですか。いいですねえ。
B:ええ、静（しず）かな公園（こうえん）のそばに家（いえ）を買（か）いました。中国人（ちゅうごくじん）がたくさんいるから、中国（ちゅうごく）のスーパーもあって便利（べんり）です。
 
a) Who are in Canada?  (B’s father)
b) Describe the living condition of the
person.   (His father bought a
house near a quiet park.  There are
many Chinese people, so there are Chinese supermarkets, which is convenient.) 　
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/345173987866.mp3" >a) When was Prof. Nakada’s seminar held? 
b) How was Prof. Nakada’s seminar?
c) When is Prof. Kitano’s seminar? 
d) Who will B go with?
</question>
<answer >A: 先週(せんしゅう）の中田先生のセミナーはよかったですねえ。
B: ええ、面白（おもしろ）くて、あまり難（むずか）しくなかったですねえ。
A:次（つぎ）の北野（きたの）先生のセミナーにも行きますか。
B:ええ、もちろん。来週（らいしゅう）の火曜日の三時ですね。そのセミナーには母（はは）も連（つ）れて行きますよ。
a) When was Prof. Nakada’s seminar held?  (Last
week)
b) How was Prof. Nakada’s seminar?  (It was
good. Interesting and not difficult)
c) When is Prof. Kitano’s seminar?   (Tuesday next week at 3)
d) Who will B go with?    (Bring her mother) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/331060834535.mp3" >a) Who is calling whom?
b) What is B doing today? Give details. 
c) What does A invite B to do? 
</question>
<answer >A: もしもし、今田です。 
B: あ、今田さん。こんにちは。
A: 林(はやし）さん、今日は何（なに）をしていますか。
B: 朝（あさ）、泳（およ）ぎに行（い）って、今、家（うち）に帰（かえ）って来（き）ました。午後（ごご）は別（べつ）にプランはありませんけど、、。
A:じゃあ、今日、晩（ばん）ご飯（はん）を食（た）べに行きませんか。おいしいレストランに連（つ）れて行きますから。
B: あ、いいですねえ、じゃあ。
 
a) Who is calling whom? (Imada called Hayashi)
b) What is B doing today? Give details. (She is at home.  She went swimming this morning and came home just now. She
doesn't have any plan in the afternoon.)
c) What does A invite B to do? (To dinner.  He will take B to a good restaurant.)　
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/135326077303.mp3" >a) How many students in Kato’s class? 
b) What is Kato’s general impression of the
students? 
c) What does A say about her students.  
</question>
<answer >A: 加藤(かとう）先生のクラスには学生は何人いますか。 
B: 男の学生が七人で、女の学生が二人です。今年（ことし）の学生は、元気（げんき）でおもしろいですよ。
A: そうですか。私のクラスの学生もよく勉強（べんきょう）していますよ。
B: それは、よかったですね。
 
a) How many students in Kato’s class?  (Seven male students, and two female students.)
b) What is Kato’s general impression of the
students?  (Students of this year
are energetic and fun.)
c) What does A say about her students.   (They are studying hard, too)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/744424786725.mp3" >a) How are the cookies? 
b) Who made them? Why?  
c) What does B offer?    
</question>
<answer >A: このクッキー、とてもおいしいです。 小（ちい）さくてかわいいですね。
B: それ、主人（しゅじん）の母（はは）が作（つく）りました。主人（しゅじん）が大好（だいす）きだから、、。
A: へえ。そうですか。
B: たくさんありますから、よかったら少（すこ）し持（も）って帰（かえ）ってください。
A: いや、いいですよ。
B: どうぞ、どうぞ。
 
a) How are the cookies?  (Tasty. Small and cute.)
b) Who made them? Why?  (B’s husband’s mother.  B’s husband likes them.)  
c) What does B offer?       (‘Please take some home if you like.’)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/417846071141.mp3" >a) What is discussed? 
b) Is B familiar with it?
</question>
<answer >A: とても古(ふる）い歌（うた）ですねえ。田中さんは、この歌（うた）を知（し）っていますか。 
B: ええ、祖母（そぼ）がよく歌（うた）っていましたから。
 
a) What is discussed?  (An old song.)
b) Is B familiar with it?  (Yes. Her grandmother used to
sing it.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/540627844472.mp3" >a) What does A ask B to do? 
b) What is B’s concern? 
</question>
<answer >A: 木村(きむら）さん、木村(きむら）さんは自転車（じてんしゃ）を持（も）っていますね。
B: ええ。あまり新（あたら）しくないですけど、ありますよ。
A: それ、週末（しゅうまつ）借（か）りてもいいですか。
B: ええ、でも、私の自転車（じてんしゃ）は小（ちい）さいですよ。私、背（せ）が低（ひく）いから、、。
A: 大丈夫（だいじょうぶ）ですよ。ありがとう！
 
a) What does A ask B to do?　
(A asked if she could borrow B’s bike this weekend.)
 
b)
What is B’s concern? 
(B’s bike is small because she is short.)
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/826196854774.mp3" >a) Where did B go? Who did she go with? 
b) How was it? 
</question>
<answer >A: 先月（せんげつ）、主人（しゅじん）と子（こ）どもと一緒（いっしょ）にキャンプをしに行きましたよ。
B: 楽（たの）しかったですか。
A: いや、夜（よる）は怖（こわ）くて、、。それに、短（みじか）いパンツをはいて行ったから、ちょっと寒（さむ）かったです。 
 a) Where did B go? Who did she go with?  (A went camping with her husband and their
child.)
b) How was it?   (Scary at night.  She wore short pants so it was cold.) 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/816647525484.mp3" >a) What event was discussed? 
b) Who went there? 
c) Who did B meet there? 
d) What does B mention about the person?  
</question>
<answer >A: 土曜日に加藤(かとう）先生のうちでパーティがありましたね。行きましたか。
B:  ええ、八人ぐらい留学生（りゅうがくせい）が来（き）て、楽（たの）しいパーティでしたよ。
A: 加藤（かとう）先生の奥（おく）さんに会（あ）いましたか。
B:  ええ。
A: どんな人ですか。
B: とっても親切（しんせつ）な人でした。中国人（ちゅうごくじん）の学生と中国語（ちゅうごくご）で話（はな）していましたよ。
  
a) What event was discussed?  (Party at Professor Kato’s house on Saturday.)b) Who went there?  (B and about eight foreign students.) 
c) Who did B meet there?   (Professor Kato’s wife.)
d) What does B mention about the person?  (Kind. She was speaking Chinese
students in Chinese.)
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/273936539030.mp3" >a) Who is being discussed?
b) Describe the person in detail.   
c) How well does A know the person? 
</question>
<answer >A: 隣（となり）の部屋（へや）に新（あたら）しい人が入（はい）りました。
B: 女の人ですか。
A: いや、男の人です。眼鏡（めがね）をかけていて、やせていますよ。
B: 背（せ）は高（たか）いですか。
A: ええ。足（あし）が長（なが）いですよ。
B: その人と話（はな）しましたか。
A: ええ、ちょっとですけど。
 
a) Who is being discussed?    (A’s new person in the
apartment.)
b) Describe the person in detail.   (A man. 
He wears glasses and thin. Tall. Long legs.)
c) How well does A know the person?  (She
talked with him a little.) 
　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　　
 
 
</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/255948586230.mp3" >a) Where is Mizuno?
b) Describe Mizuno. 
</question>
<answer >A: あの背（せ）が高（たか）い女の人が水野（みずの）さんですか。
B:  いや、水野（みず）さんはあの小（ちい）さい人ですよ。A: え？どこにいますか。
B:　ピアノの前（まえ）です。
A: あの髪（かみ）が短（みじか）い人ですか。
B:  ええ。 
 a) Where is Mizuno?  (In front of a piano.)
b) Describe Mizuno.  (Small. Short hair.)
</answer>
</exercise>
</exercises>
