<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<exercises>
<instruction>Answer the questions based on the conversation.  A
 refers to the first speaker, B the second.  Click "Show" for the 
scripts and the answers. </instruction>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/390977413467.mp3" >a) What does A ask for?  Why?
b) What is the problem with B’s offer? 
c) What is B’s suggestion? 
</question>
<answer >A: ああ、喉のどがかわいた。何か冷つめたい飲み物ものある？B: そこに野菜やさいのジュースがあるでしょう？A: これ、甘あますぎて嫌きらいなんだ。ほかに何かない？B: じゃあ、悪わるいけど、何か好きな物もの、買ってきてください。a) What does A ask for?  Why? (cold drink, because he is thirsty)b) What is the problem with B’s offer?  (A doesn’t like the vegetable juice they have because it’s too sweet)c) What is B’s suggestion?  (Go buy something A likes) </answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/468513814107.mp3" >a) What was said in the weather forecast?  Give details. 
</question>
<answer >A: 今朝の天気予報よほう、聞きましたか？B: ええ、今日は晴はれ、時々曇くもりだって言っていましたよ。A: 雨は？B: 今日は降ふらないだろうけど、明日から二三日降るだろうって言っていました。a) What was said in the weather forecast?  Give details.  (Today: sunny/sometimes cloudy.  It will probably rain for two to three days starting from tomorrow.)</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/818646215674.mp3" >a)Who is under discussion.
b) How does A think of the person?
c) Why does B know the person? 
d) What is B’s suggestion about A’s behavior. 
</question>
<answer >A: あの人、素敵すてきねぇ。B: ああ、高橋君たかはしくん？A: え、知ってる人？ B:もちろん。かっこよくてテニスが上手な有名人。A: ええ？私、初はじめて見たよ。かっこいいねぇ。B:  ちょっと、じろじろ見ない方がいいと思うけど。a)Who is under discussion. (Takahashi) b) How does A think of A?c) Why does B know the person?  (he is a famous person because he is good looking and very good at tennis.  )d) What is B’s suggestion about A’s behavior.  (A’d better not star at Takahashi)</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/488763282614.mp3" >
</question>
<answer >A: もうすぐなので、ステージの横よこで待っまていてください。B: すみません、もう一度お手洗あらいに行ってきてもいいですか。A: またですか。B: ええ、緊張きんちょうしてお腹なかが痛いたいんです。A: 人の前で話すのは初はじめてですか？B: はい、そうなんです。a) What is A asking B to do? (To wait next to the stage, since B’s turn is coming up soon.)b) What does B want to do now? (Go to the bathroom again.)c) What is B’s condition now.   (Her stomach aches because she is nervous.)d) What is the explanation for B’s current condition?  (First time to talk in front of people)</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/986663599572.mp3" >a) What is B’s current condition? 
b) What is A’s suggestion? 
c) What is B’ response? 
d) What is A offering? 
</question>
<answer >A: どうしたんですか。B: さっきから頭あたまがすごく痛くて。A:  熱ねつは？B: 熱はないと思うんですけど。A:ちょっと休んだ方がいいですよ。B: ええ、でも、もうすぐプロジェクトの締しめ切きりなんです。A: 何か手伝つだいましょうか。B: じゃあ、悪わるいですけど、これ、お願ねがいしてもいいですか。A: ええ、もちろん。a) What is B’s current condition? (Headache with no fever.)b) What is A’s suggestion? (A should rest a little.)c) What is B’ response? (The project deadline is approaching)  d) What is A offering? (To help B)  </answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question  >a)What happened to B yesterday? 
b)What are the reasons for yesterday’s incident?  Give details. 
c) What is A’s reaction to the situation?   Give details. 
</question>
<answer >A: 目が赤いよ。何かあった？B: 昨日きのう彼かれと別れたんだ。A:  ええ？けんかしたの？B:  ううん。彼、私にはもう興味きょうみがないって。A:   彼がそう言ったの？B: うん、私と一緒いっしょにいるのがあまり楽しくなくなったって言ってた。A: そうか。残念ざんねんだね。でも、多分たぶんすぐに新しい彼ができるよ。さっちゃんは人気があるから、さっちゃんの彼になりたがってる人は多おおいと思うよ。a)What happened to B yesterday? (B broke up with her boyfriend.)b)What are the reasons for yesterday’s incident?  Give details. (B’s boyfriend has lost interest in B.   He  says that being with B has become not much fun.)c) What is A’s reaction to the situation?   Give details.  (Too bad, but A thinks that B will find a new boyfriend soon.  A is popular and B thinks that there are many people who want to become her boyfriend.)</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/743751975781.mp3" >a) What is B doing now? 
b) What is B’s health condition?  
c) What is A’s suggestion? 
d) What is B’s reaction to A’s suggestion?  
e) What is A’s concern?  
</question>
<answer >A: あ、西田さん、まだ仕事しているんですか。B: ええ。A:  風邪かぜ引ひいているんでしょう？今日は早く帰った方がいいですよ。B: そうしたいんですが、これから用事ようじがあって渋谷しぶやまで行かなければいけないんですよ。A: 西田さんは本当にいつも忙いそがしいですねぇ。働きすぎて病気にならないでくださいね。B: 大丈夫ですよ。a) What is B doing now? (Still working.)b) What is B’s health condition?  (has a cold)c) What is A’s suggestion? (A should go home early today.)d) What is B’s reaction to A’s suggestion?  (Would like to go home, but has an errand and have to go to Shibuya now)e) What is A’s concern?  (B gets sick from overworking.)</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/847982632768.mp3" >a) Who is under discussion? 
b) What does A think of the person? 
c) What is the current relationship between the person and B?   
</question>
<answer >A: みかちゃん、あの素敵すてきな彼かれは元気？B: うん、、私ね、このごろちょっと心配しんぱいしているんだ。A:  どうして？B:   彼がちょっと冷つめたくなったから。A:  ええ、本当？B:  うん、多分私と別れたがっていると思うんだけど、私はまだ彼が大好きだから。。a) Who is under discussion? (B's boyfriend)b) What does A think of the person? (nice)c) What is the current relationship between the person and B? (B's boyfriend has gotten cold recently and apparently wants to break up with B, while B still likes him a lot.)</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/217650603809.mp3" >a) Why is A apologizing? 
b) Explain what happened to A. 
c)What is the current situation? Give details.  
d) What does A ask B to do? 
</question>
<answer >A: 遅おそくなってすみません。B: 何かあったんですか。A:  電車の中で財布さいふをなくして、駅えきの人と話したり、銀行ぎんこうに電話かけたりしなきゃいけなかったんです。B: それは大変でしたねぇ。財布さいふはありましたか？A: いえ、駅の人が、まだ誰だれもまだ見つけていないと言っていたから、心配しているんですけど。。B: そうですか。a) Why is A apologizing? (Because A is late.)b) Explain what happened to A. (He lost his wallet in a train and had to talk to people in the station and call his bank.)c)What is the current situation? Give details.  (B’s wallet is still missing.  B is worried because a person at the station said that nobody has found it yet. )d) What does A ask B to do? (‘Please give the recipe to me, too’.)</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/189464084644.mp3" >a) Who is under discussion?  
b) What is A’s concern?  
c) What is B’s explanation about the person’s condition?   
d) What is the reasoning for B’s explanation?  
e) What  does A think about the situation?  
f) What is B’s reaction?  
</question>
<answer >A: 山本さん、今日は元気がなかったですねぇ。B: ああ、山本さんは多分二日酔よいで頭あたまが痛いたかったんでしょう。A:  二日酔い？B: ええ、昨日きのうの晩ばん、町に出かけて、飲み過すぎたって言っていたから。A:体からだに悪わるいから、お酒さけはできるだけやめた方がいいと思いますけどねぇ。B: まあタバコよりはいいでしょうけどね。a) Who is under discussion?  (Yamamoto)b) What is A’s concern?  (Yamamoto did not look well.) c) What is B’s explanation about the person’s condition?   (Probably Yamamoto had a headache due to hangover.)d) What is the reasoning for B’s explanation?  (Yamamoto said that he had gone out to a town  and drank too much last night.)e) What  does A think about the situation?  (A thinks that one  had better quit drinking as much as possible, since it’s bad for ones’ health.)f) What is B’s reaction?  (B thinks that drinking is probably better than smoking.)</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/795149265629.mp3" >a)What’s A asking B about?  Give details.  
b) What’s B’s response.  
c) What’s A’s reaction?  
</question>
<answer >A: 今住すんでいる部屋へやが狭せますぎるので、新しい部屋へやを見つけたいと思っているんですが、どこかいい所知りませんか。B: あ、来月からイギリスに留学りゅうがくする友達だちがいるんだけど、彼女の部屋を借かりるのはどう？興味きょうみある？A: ええ、 是非ぜひその人を紹介しょうかいしてください。a)What’s A asking B about?  Give details.  (if B knows a good place for A, whose current room is too small and therefore A wants to find a new room)b) What’s B’s response.  (Suggesting A rent a room of B’s friend, who will go abroad to study from next month.)c) What’s A’s reaction?  (Very interested.  Says “Please introduce that person to her by all means.”)</answer>
</exercise>
<exercise>
<question audio="audio/495226758140.mp3" >a)    What’s A’s invitation?  
b)    What’s B’s response?  Explain the reasons in details. 
</question>
<answer >A: 来学期らいがっき、月曜日の２時からの経済けいざいのクラスを一緒いっしょに取とらない？B: ああ、その時間は、都合つごうが悪わるいんだ。A: ほかのクラスを取るの？B:うん、今学期こんがっきの試験しけんの成績せいせきが悪わるすぎて、パスできなかったから、来学期もう一度歴史れきしのクラスを取らなくちゃいけないんだ。B: ああ、それは残念ざんねん。a)    What’s A’s invitation?   (To take Monday 2:00 economics class  together next semester.)b)    What’s B’s response?  Explain the reasons in details. (The time won’t work.  She has to retake the history class next semester, because she couldn’t pass it by receiving poor grades this semester.)</answer>
</exercise>
</exercises>
